<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-28T11:59:28+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Thinking Out Loud</title><subtitle>Exploring ideas about engineering, mathematics, computing, Wittgenstien and art.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Future is Local Farming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-future-is-local/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future is Local Farming" /><published>2020-07-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-future-is-local</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-future-is-local/">&lt;p&gt;The village where I live is surrounded by arable land which I enjoy walking through on the public paths.  Walking around a field of potatoes a thought came to mind: after picking the potatoes they will probably travel tens if not hundreds of miles to be cleaned and graded before returning to my local shop where I can by them - why can they not go straight to the shop?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something needs to change if we are going to win the fight against climate change, improve our health and have more interesting work. But how could it be done? First there needs to be enough land surrounding a village to support all of its households with food and other produce. Following guidance from the self sufficiency expert &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Seymour_(author)&quot;&gt;John Seymour&lt;/a&gt;, around one acre per household without cows or five acres with animals is needed. In the village where I live there are roughly five hundred households and therefore the land required would be about five hundred acres. Therefore land wise it would be possible for local farmers to support the village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce the reliance on chemicals for increasing crop yields the emerging technology of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/features/working-with-robots-to-transform-farming&quot;&gt;robotics and AI&lt;/a&gt; could be used. For example the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smallrobotcompany.com/&quot;&gt;Small Robot Company&lt;/a&gt;, who are working with the National Trust, are developing robots that can plant, monitor and treat crops autonomously.  Robots can &lt;a href=&quot;https://builtin.com/robotics/farming-agricultural-robots&quot;&gt;harvest a range of crops&lt;/a&gt; ranging from lettuces to raspberries.  Once harvested there are different ways for processing the produce locally, for example it could be processed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eufic.org/en/collaboration/article/fox-food-processing-in-a-box-innovative-local-fruit-and-vegetable-processing-for-a-sustainable-future&quot;&gt;in a shipping container type boxes&lt;/a&gt; which would either be situated on the farm or in the village. Shipping containers are already used in small bakeries such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dockerbakery.com/&quot;&gt;Docker Bakery&lt;/a&gt; in Folkestone. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.farmbusiness.co.uk/livestock/dairy/new-on-farm-milk-pasteuriser-range-launched.html&quot;&gt;Milk could be pasteurised on the farm&lt;/a&gt; and containers could be used to house equipment for preserving surplus produce. Delivery of the produce to the customer would use robots similar to those used in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/long_reads/delivery-robot-milton-keynes-coronavirus-a9537121.html&quot;&gt;Milton Keynes to deliver pizzas&lt;/a&gt;. Customers could register their daily purchases of the products via an app and the seasonal demand would be analysed using AI so that that the amount of annual planting would be optimised to reduce waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There would be many benefits for such a system. If the robots were powered via solar panels they would probably be much smaller than the large tractors that can be seen currently in the fields therefore field size could be reduced and hedge rows re-introduced which would improve biodiversity. Local jobs would be created to develop, build and and maintain the robotics and AI systems as well as growing and processing the produce. New skills would be required in developing technology such as 3D printing which would be used to replace parts on the robots. Old skills would be re-discovered such as pickling surplus produce or making containers from locally produced willow for the robots to transport the produce to the doorstep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there are a few problems with the vision. First there is what I have labeled the ‘avocado problem’ which is crops that we cannot produce in the UK because of our climate e.g. tea.  Some form of trade will still be required. However with increasing breakthroughs in biotechnology there may be a way of growing avocados and other plants in the UK. Another aspect is the seasonality of the produce.  Customers want strawberries all the year round but if the price for non-seasonal crops reflected the true cost, for example the impact on the environment of shipping them thousands of miles, then seasonality of home grown fruit and vegetables would become more financially attractive. Anyway I have found that strawberries being available only at certain times of the year makes them more delicious!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vision is also based on a village or small town surrounded by fields but it would have to be developed in a different way for large towns or cities. Ideas such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fwi.co.uk/arable/crop-management/why-vertical-farming-is-growing-in-the-uk&quot;&gt;‘vertical’ farming&lt;/a&gt; and exciting projects carried out in Singapore which show that crops can be grown on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.straitstimes.com/singapore/veggies-to-be-grown-at-more-hdb-carpark-rooftops&quot;&gt;carpark rooftops&lt;/a&gt;.  Or growing mushrooms &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crumbsmag.com/features/552_fun-guy/&quot;&gt;underground&lt;/a&gt; in a city show that there is potential to grow food in large urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long and complex supply chains that are used to bring food to our house are based on high carbon miles and they are also weak to disruption which have been shown during the Covid-19 pandemic. There are many advantages of locally produced food: significant reduction in carbon miles which will reduce global warming, fresh produce which will improve health, redesigning of farming systems will increase biodiversity, outdoor projects where the local community can get involved will improve mental as well as physical health, and more interesting jobs will give greater job satisfaction.  Maybe one day potatoes picked that morning could only be a click away - now there is a thought.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Robots" /><category term="AI" /><category term="3D Printing" /><category term="Shipping Containers" /><category term="Biodiversity" /><summary type="html">The village where I live is surrounded by arable land which I enjoy walking through on the public paths. Walking around a field of potatoes a thought came to mind: after picking the potatoes they will probably travel tens if not hundreds of miles to be cleaned and graded before returning to my local shop where I can by them - why can they not go straight to the shop?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/the-future-is-local.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22AGRITECTURE%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://www.agritecture.com/blog/2019/1/9/new-wave-of-agtech-startups-are-putting-robots-in-the-fields%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cooking The World Green</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/manifesto-recipe-book/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cooking The World Green" /><published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/manifesto-recipe-book</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/manifesto-recipe-book/">&lt;p&gt;Every second of the day millions of people around the world are preparing and cooking food. It is an activity that has been going on since the beginning of time. But if we are going to win the battle against &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-24021772&quot;&gt;climate change&lt;/a&gt; then what we eat and how we prepare it will have to change. Could a book about cooking ignite that change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years have I gathered a couple of shelves of cookery books. In amongst the collection are the ‘go to books’ from Delia Smith, Marry Berry and Jamie Oliver which I head for when struggling to prepare an interesting meal. But these books reinforce our existing lifestyle with enticing pictures of food and text that reflect either how we live or how we would like to live. All of these books fail to make any comment about the environmental impact of the food that that is being prepared. There are a few cooking books available that claim &lt;a href=&quot;https://theecologist.org/2011/jun/13/five-best-environmentally-friendly-cookbooks&quot;&gt;environmental credentials&lt;/a&gt; with titles such as: &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/Seaweed_and_Eat_It.html?id=8PMb-EeRG9QC&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&quot;&gt;Seaweed and Eat It: A Family Foraging and Cooking Adventure&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ooW0GQAACAAJ&amp;amp;dq=The+Acorn+House+Cookbook:+Good+Food+from+Field+to+Fork&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjf24aK7ZTqAhXFrHEKHe3ZAyUQ6AEwAXoECAEQAg&quot;&gt;The Acorn House Cookbook: Good Food from Field to Fork&lt;/a&gt; and some by celebrities such as Hugh Fearnley Whittingstall’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=5p_EDq4rWz4C&amp;amp;dq=River+Cottage+Everyday&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiFyPbG7ZTqAhUCSxUIHeOvAPcQ6AEwAHoECAAQAg&quot;&gt;River Cottage Everday&lt;/a&gt; but it is not clear whether they are selling a utopian life rather than changing what we grow and eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooking books are a major part of the book selling industry. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npd.com/wps/portal/npd/us/news/press-releases/2018/cookbook-category-sales-rose-21-percent-year-over-year-the-npd-group-says/&quot;&gt;best seller&lt;/a&gt; can achieve around one million copies and therefore it is a good medium to create a change in what we eat. So this is my idea. It would have more impact if a cookery book could be compiled from leading people who are proactive in reducing our impact on the environment.  It would be a recipe book with a difference. Each contributor would write about the importance of their favourite meal and how from their perspective it has helped them in the fight against climate change. To select the contributors a few criteria would be required. First they must be able to make the meal themselves. They must understand how the ingredients that they are using has impacted on the environment. Their reflections about their meal could include when they first had the meal, or how it kick started their desire to fight for the planet, or was it a meal that changed another person into a campaigner for a better world?  The recipes could range from ‘something’ on toast to a meal made from ingredients that would normally be thrown out. They would be encouraged to write about their own personal dilemmas for example I enjoy milk products but with the need to reduce our reliance on cows what could they write to persuade me to give up on cheese and milk?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of names that come to mind as contributors such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldlandtrust.org/patrons/sir-david-attenborough/&quot;&gt;Sir David Attenborough&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greta_Thunberg&quot;&gt;Greta Thunberg&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chrispackham.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Chris Packham&lt;/a&gt;. But there are many more people around the world who are making a contribution in the fight against global warming.  For example &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cleanseas.org/impact/young-champions-help-stem-marine-plastic&quot;&gt;Miao Wang&lt;/a&gt; is working with divers to spread awareness about the perils of plastic pollution.  What comforting meal would she make after a long day of diving and how does it avoid the use of  plastic containers? Another contributor could be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angela_Merkel&quot;&gt;Angela Merkel&lt;/a&gt; who is the only major politician left who helped develop the original global warming agreement at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyoto_Protocol&quot;&gt;Kyoto in 1997&lt;/a&gt;. But actions speak louder than words and she is leading Germany to turn away from coal and oil, and setting the highest targets for renewables and emission cuts. After a long day of politicking does the Chancellor of Germany sit down for a favourite national meal of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thespruceeats.com/simple-german-rice-pudding-1446849&quot;&gt;rice pudding&lt;/a&gt;? It is important to include those who need a voice on the world stage and one possible could be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globaljustice.org.uk/blog/2017/apr/17/un-needs-start-supporting-rights-peasants-around-world&quot;&gt;Henry Saragih&lt;/a&gt; who is a small farmer who is taking on the Indonesian government and the palm oil barons of Sumatra and Kalimantan. Companies with links to government are devastating vast areas of Indonesia and southeast Asia to grow palm oil to supply Europe’s cars and kitchens with biofuel and cooking oils, and Saragih is one of the few people standing in their path. What does he cook for himself after a hard day of campaigning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cookery book proposed would be a sort of manifesto for what and how we should eat to reduce our impact on the environment. And when the many millions of people sit down to plan their next meal then let us hope that they will be reminded by such a book of how much they can play in beating climate change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Environment" /><category term="Cooking" /><category term="Baking" /><summary type="html">Every second of the day millions of people around the world are preparing and cooking food. It is an activity that has been going on since the beginning of time. But if we are going to win the battle against climate change then what we eat and how we prepare it will have to change. Could a book about cooking ignite that change?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/manifesto-recipe-book.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22CNN%20Health%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://edition.cnn.com/2016/05/05/health/healthy-vegetable-cooking/index.html%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">After The Great Pause</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/after-the-great-pause/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="After The Great Pause" /><published>2020-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/after-the-great-pause</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/after-the-great-pause/">&lt;p&gt;During &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lockdown&quot;&gt;lockdown&lt;/a&gt; our kitchen was at full steam, flour availability permitting, producing cakes, chocolate biscuits and bread. But we ran into a problem.  A cupboard door wouldn’t close properly because a spring had broken. The search to find a replacement part discovered weaknesses in UK manufacturing but also created thoughts about its future after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opendemocracy.net/en/oureconomy/great-pause/&quot;&gt;Great Pause&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some instructions off the web and pressing a few clips I took the broken part out of the cupboard. It was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://industrialgassprings.com/uk/&quot;&gt;spring&lt;/a&gt; made in Germany. After deciphering a few symbols I headed back onto the web and found a few stockists in the UK. But when I approached them I received the standard get out reply of “we no longer have these in stock.”  I eventually contacted the original manufacturer in Germany and ordered a new part that would take four to six weeks to arrive because it had to be made to order. Curiosity took over and I wanted to find out of if there were any UK manufacturers of equivalent springs. I found a few companies that supplied them to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://industrialgassprings.com/uk/our-history/&quot;&gt;motor and aviation industry&lt;/a&gt; but they didn’t appear to have any for a kitchen cupboard. What has happened to the manufacturing capability in the UK?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing was once the bedrock of economic activity in the UK but has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newstatesman.com/culture/culture/2013/01/meeting-our-makers-britain%E2%80%99s-long-industrial-decline&quot;&gt;slowly declined&lt;/a&gt; over tens of years.  In 1952, it produced a third of the national output, employed 40 per cent of the workforce and made up a quarter of world manufacturing exports. Today, manufacturing in the UK accounts for just 11 per cent of GDP, employs only 8 per cent of the workforce and sells 2 per cent of the world’s manufacturing exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current Covid-19 pandemic has emphasised the weakness in UK manufacturing with our inability to produce medical equipment for frontline workers. However, there are signs of hope as it quickly responded to the pandemic with many companies, large and small, coming together to manufacture &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2020/apr/05/ventilator-crisis-lands-britains-manufacturers-with-greatest-test&quot;&gt;ventilators&lt;/a&gt;, PPE and hand sanitisers. This flexibility has shown that there is still some life in UK manufacturing and is the basis for building itself a stronger future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When lockdown starts to ease there is another greater challenge facing us. Climate change, like Covid-19, will affect us all. Lockdown has given an insight into what a green future would look like with reductions in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.standard.co.uk/news/world/positive-impact-environment-coronavirus-lockdown-a4404751.html&quot;&gt;carbon emissions and reduced carbon miles&lt;/a&gt;. But for many industries once the pandemic is under control it will not be back to ‘business as usual’ because they will have to rebuild against a background of new demands. Now is the time for UK manufacturing to turn green and rebuild itself to lead the way in combating climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many new areas that manufacturing could exploit so that it can rebuild itself. One area that has been highlighted during the pandemic is medical equipment. The UK imports around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.export.gov/apex/article2?id=United-Kingdom-Medical-Equipment&quot;&gt;40%&lt;/a&gt; of its medical equipment and given its strategic importance for future pandemics then there is an opportunity for manufacturers to increase its production in this area. Another area is the development of new medical equipment ranging from robotic surgeons to quick home tests for diseases. Transportation will require a massive switch to electric powered vehicles in all their shapes and sizes. There may be opportunities for new types of vehicles such as unmanned small vans that can deliver goods from local suppliers to doorsteps which would reduce carbon miles down. The UK produces about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.countryfile.com/news/can-the-uk-feed-itself-after-brexit/&quot;&gt;60%&lt;/a&gt; of its own food. Manufacturing could develop new equipment to plant and harvest vegetables which will be in greater demand as consumption moves away from animals. New technology could be integrated into manufacturing processes to make them more adaptable for changes in demand for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/3D_printing&quot;&gt;3D Printing&lt;/a&gt;. Another example is the future design of equipment could include re-cycling so that old parts are returned to the manufacturer to be used in new equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the changes required to rebuild manufacturing will take some time and therefore can not be left to market forces because they are too short-term.  Government intervention is required to provide a framework for the regeneration of manufacturing. There are many forms that its policies needs to take. First government policy must have a stronger green element to drive manufacturing towards a green economy. Policies need to reduce cheap imports which ultimately export jobs which has undermined UK manufacturing for many years. If ‘cheap’ goods are demanded then government policy should encourage the development of skills in automation and robot systems to systems that will reduce the production of the goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another change in government policy is education. It needs to be radically overhauled with a stronger emphasis on STEM, biology and the environment.  The education system should integrate the arts into the design so that whatever is produced enhances the environment that we live in both physically and emotionally.  Their policy must include re-training for people at every stage of their lives so that for those who are interested can stay up to date with the latest manufacturing technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the manufacturing industry accounts for the majority of R&amp;amp;D expenditure in the UK (65% in 2018), this is down from 84% in 1985.  Universities should concentrate on teaching and research and not include spin-offs for new technology which has only been &lt;a href=&quot;https://techtransfercentral.com/2010/07/14/survey-suggests-top-10-reasons-university-start-ups-fail/&quot;&gt;partially successful&lt;/a&gt;. If the research  shows any promise for new technologies then it can be transferred to something like the government’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://catapult.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Catapult Network&lt;/a&gt; where business could get free access to the technology if they meet certain criteria. For example, the business should demonstrate that it is strong enough to sustain a shock in its earnings, as is happening during the Covid-19 pandemic, before they get access to the new technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK manufacturing response to the pandemic has shown that there are signs that when the Great Pause is over it can have a stronger future in building the green economy. And next time I have a breakdown in our kitchen I can return the part to a UK manufacturer for repair!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Mental Health" /><category term="Manufacturing" /><category term="Training" /><category term="Education" /><category term="Government" /><category term="Covid-19" /><summary type="html">During lockdown our kitchen was at full steam, flour availability permitting, producing cakes, chocolate biscuits and bread. But we ran into a problem. A cupboard door wouldn’t close properly because a spring had broken. The search to find a replacement part discovered weaknesses in UK manufacturing but also created thoughts about its future after the Great Pause.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/after-the-great-pause.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Make%20it%20British%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://makeitbritish.co.uk/opinion/manufacture-your-product-in-the-uk/%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Future Of The Equation $R$</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-future-of-R/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future Of The Equation $R$" /><published>2020-04-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-future-of-R</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-future-of-R/">&lt;p&gt;A simple equation has changed the way that we live. It is having a greater impact than any of the ground breaking theories from science. The reproduction number $R$ is being used to change our behaviours to reduce the spread of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/covid-19-pandemic&quot;&gt;Covid-19&lt;/a&gt; virus and will leave its mark on us well into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments around the world are using $R$ to guide their actions in controlling the spread of the Covid-19 virus. The version of $R$ that they are using is the “basic” reproduction number, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sounds/play/m000hp44&quot;&gt;$R_0$ ( or R nought)&lt;/a&gt; and it is the situation when when no one has been vaccinated, no one has had the disease before and there is no way to control the disease. Calculating $R$ is a complicated process but comes down to three components: how long a person is infected, how often they come in contact with others and how the disease is spread.  A long period of infection will increase the value of $R$. If a person comes in contact with lots of people then they increase the value of $R$ as well as how it is transmitted for example airborne diseases will give a higher value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of $R$ is used to assess the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dictionary.com/browse/contagiousness&quot;&gt;contagiousness&lt;/a&gt; of a disease. For example if $R$ has a value of 2 then one infected person will pass the virus onto another two other people who in turn will each pass it onto another two and so on. If $R$ is less than 1 then the spread of the virus will decline. &lt;a href=&quot;https://labblog.uofmhealth.org/rounds/how-scientists-quantify-intensity-of-an-outbreak-like-covid-19&quot;&gt;Calculating&lt;/a&gt; $R$ requires complex mathematical modelling, lots of data and powerful computers which results, at best, in an average for its value. For example $R$ has a value of between  1 - 2 for the common cold, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Severe_acute_respiratory_syndrome&quot;&gt;SARS&lt;/a&gt; is 2 - 5, and at the early stages of Covid-19 it varied between 1.4 - 5.7. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/coronavirus-action-plan/coronavirus-action-plan-a-guide-to-what-you-can-expect-across-the-uk&quot;&gt;UK Government’s action plan&lt;/a&gt; is aimed at reducing $R$ by breaking the transmission of the virus with regular messages by washing hands, enforcing social distancing and a lockdown for non-essential workers. Early signs, but unconfirmed, is that $R$ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theweek.co.uk/coronavirus/106759/what-is-the-coronavirus-r-value-and-why-does-it-matter&quot;&gt;could be between 1 and 0.5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is the impact of reducing $R$ which is having a dramatic impact on our lives. Health and Social Care systems are having to respond to the virus in ways that were never expected as they fight to save as many lives as possible. Non-essential parts of the UK economy have hit a brick wall while other sectors plummeted to their lowest levels of activity since records began. There is a similar picture around the world which is slowing global trade and will ultimately reduce economic activity in national economies. The response of governments to the pandemic is starting to raise fundamental questions about how we live and work. How will those people who are identified as key workers be valued in the future by society? Will government intervention in the economy during the crisis remain for many years ahead?  Is their proposed tracking and tracing app a step too far in monitoring society? How much do we really know about the human body and how it works and how its it translated into medicine Will the growth of the digital economy accelerate through on-line entertainment and delivering more goods to our doorsteps but will it go on to change the type of work? Are the days of commuting over? Will on-line learning become an integral part of education? Will the remote monitoring and support of patients be a few clicks from a doctors desk? Should the length of supply chains be reduced to within our shores and we make more of our own products so that we can respond quickly to future crisis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If $R$ had stayed buried in technical papers and and discussed in specialist conferences with the occasional  discussion at a government strategic committee then we would never of heard of it.  But now it has made its way into everyones lives, through the actions of governments, then lots of questions are bubbling to the surface. The longer that the fight against Covid-19 goes on then the greater the public will require action in answering these questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a century ago Einstein’s equation $E=mc^2$ was brought to the publics attention which heralded the start of a  revolution in our understanding of how the universe works, from planets down to the quantum level, which created the technology that has shaped our lives. $R$ has signalled the start of another science revolution but this time it will be in our understanding of how we live together and down to the level cell activity s which will change our future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="R0" /><category term="Covid-19" /><category term="Reproduction Number" /><summary type="html">A simple equation has changed the way that we live. It is having a greater impact than any of the ground breaking theories from science. The reproduction number $R$ is being used to change our behaviours to reduce the spread of the Covid-19 virus and will leave its mark on us well into the future.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/R-nought.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22THE%20CONVERSATION%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://theconversation.com/how-to-flatten-the-curve-of-coronavirus-a-mathematician-explains-133514%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sustainable Consumer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-sustainable-consumer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sustainable Consumer" /><published>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-sustainable-consumer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-sustainable-consumer/">&lt;p&gt;At a recent meeting of the World Economic Forum in Davos, HRH Prince of Wales delivered a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.princeofwales.gov.uk/speech/keynote-speech-delivered-hrh-prince-wales-world-economic-forum-davos-switzerland&quot;&gt;keynote speech&lt;/a&gt; about combating climate change. In the speech one statistic caught my attention: “With consumers controlling an estimated 60% of global G.D.P., people around the world have the power to drive the transformation to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sustainable_markets&quot;&gt;sustainable markets&lt;/a&gt;.” As a consumer do I really have the power to change the world for the better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speech was aimed at governments, businesses and other organisations and was strategic in nature but what is needed is a translation from the high level ideas into to what it means for how we spend our money. The first question that I asked was do I really control 60% of my income? A quick &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Back-of-the-envelope_calculation&quot;&gt;back-of-the-envelop calculation&lt;/a&gt; using some average numbers:
the UK’s Gross Domestic Product for 2019 was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/281744/gdp-of-the-united-kingdom-uk-since-2000/&quot;&gt;£2.21 trillion pounds&lt;/a&gt; and the total tax receipts including VAT was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ukpublicspending.co.uk/&quot;&gt;£821 billion pounds&lt;/a&gt; which gives around 63% which was left for us to spend as I wish. However, there are certain things that we have to purchase by law for example car insurance and TV licence, and other requirements e.g. house insurance, therefore very roughly it is correct that we control how we spend 60% of our income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next question is what exactly is a sustainable market? After all isn’t growing food not sustainable?  The farmer grows a crop and holds back some seed to grow the crop the following year.  Is that not a form of sustainability? However, with increasing mechanisation and automation in agriculture, with its subsequent increase in the Carbon footprint along with overworking of the soil ( which the experts claim that we only have around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/only-60-years-of-farming-left-if-soil-degradation-continues/&quot;&gt;60 years of harvesting left&lt;/a&gt; ) it is not as sustainable as I thought. A quick web search produced the following description for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sustainable_markets&quot;&gt;sustainable markets&lt;/a&gt;: “can be loosely defined as those that contribute to stronger livelihoods and more sustainable environments. In linking with the pursuit of ‘sustainable development’, such markets have a multiple focus on social, environmental and economic outcomes. Sustainable markets aim to reflect the true costs (or externalities) of natural resource degradation, environmental pollution, and promote just and safe labour practices.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do I know that the goods and services that I purchase are sustainable? There are two aspects for any goods or services: how the item is produced and how we consume it. For example buying a DVD: how sustainable is the method of manufacturing, sales, playing it and its final disposal? The same question can be asked about each item that we purchase which can cover &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.moneysavingexpert.com/banking/Budget-planning/#bplanner&quot;&gt;hundreds of products and services&lt;/a&gt;) ranging from a cup of coffee to holidays. The operation of national and local governments and organisations such as charities can fall under this question. The Prince of Wales emphasis this point in his speech “ … we cannot expect consumers to make sustainable choices if these choices are not clearly laid before them. As consumers increasingly demand sustainable products, they deserve to be told more about product lifecycles, supply chains and production methods. For a transition to take place, being socially and environmentally conscious cannot only be for those who can afford it. If all the true costs are taken into account, being socially and environmentally responsible should be the least expensive option because it leaves the smallest footprint behind. We must communicate better with consumers about the sustainability of the goods, services and investments we offer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prince of Wales’ keynote speech outlines a ten point plan to achieve sustainable markets which I believe will be a start to combatting climate change and I hope that governments, business and other organisations start to implement ASAP. In the meantime I shall be taking my spending power and asking questions about the sustainability of the products and services that I buy - I will keep you up to date with what I find.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Davos" /><category term="Economic Forum" /><summary type="html">At a recent meeting of the World Economic Forum in Davos, HRH Prince of Wales delivered a keynote speech about combating climate change. In the speech one statistic caught my attention: “With consumers controlling an estimated 60% of global G.D.P., people around the world have the power to drive the transformation to sustainable markets.” As a consumer do I really have the power to change the world for the better?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/the-sustainable-consumer.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22UTZ%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://utz.org/better-business-hub/sourcing-sustainable-products/sustainability-no-longer-novelty-outstrips-conventional-markets/%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We Need More Passionate People</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/passionate-people/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Need More Passionate People" /><published>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/passionate-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/passionate-people/">&lt;p&gt;I am interested in a wide range of subjects: the philosopher Wittgenstein, baking, poetry, mathematics, fishing. Quite a mix. But I claim no in-depth knowledge in any of these subjects.  However, when I meet people who are passionate about a subject they inspire me to add it to my already long list!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example cropped up recently when I was attending a fly fishing show. The show was full of stands selling hooks, feathers, furs, tying tools, books and many other things that I wasn’t aware that I needed to tie a fly. In amongst the stands were tables where experienced fly tyers patiently answered my very basic questions. In the middle of one hall there was a large square where fly tyers were seated demonstrating their skill. As I slowly walked around them, asking myself whether I would ever reach their level of skill, a small group had gathered around one tyer so I joined in. He was delicately tying a fly that was so small we were all straining forward to try and see. At each each stage he explained why he was selecting the materials, how he was using the tools and enjoyed answering questions. Later in the day he was giving a talk about the history of the type of fly that he was interested in and how its design had developed over the years from the introduction of new materials, tools and techniques. The talk was packed and in my opinion it was the best of the day. After the show I bought the fly tyers book which opened my eyes to new things to be learned and is so well written that I am sure that a non fly tyer would enjoy it: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.northcountryflies.com/the-north-country-fly/&quot;&gt;The North Country Fly – Yorkshire’s Soft Hackle Tradition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who are passionate about their subject can crop up unexpectedly. For example we had a company install a new garage door.  The company owner took us through the manufacturing history of our old doors, what was wrong with them and the advantages of the new doors. He also took into account how the new doors would affect the overall appearance of the house. He was passionate about garage doors and we felt that he could have spent most of the day discussing them! On a more regular basis we buy cheese from a stall in our local market. The stall holder will take time to explain the history, recipe, and the importance of cows milk to the quality of the cheese and will let us sample the different types. Although it can take over five minutes to buy a piece of cheese we always feel that we have learned something about the art of cheese making and look forward to our next purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passionate people concentrate on the ‘why’ as well as the ‘how’ and pick the correct level of communication for their audience. They have a command of detail, including the history of their subject as well as being knowledgable about the people who are also involved in the same area. They tend to be self motivated and whether they have a university degree about their subject is secondary. They are also passionate about sharing their subject.  But it is interesting to note that the passion of a person can be blunted by the media. For example, I am sure if I met Sir David Attenborough or Prof Brian Cox then their passion would be more effective whereas on the TV or Radio it is not at the same level as some of the people that I mentioned above. Therefore it is important to meet passionate people face to face. Another subtle difference is between somebody who is enthusiastic and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2016/07/this-is-what-passionate-people-do-differently/&quot;&gt;passionate&lt;/a&gt; person. An enthusiastic person can come across as excitable and showy about a subject and seem to be trying to sell it whereas a passionate person brings their subject to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world that seems to be full of experts and enthusiasts who are just a few clicks away who spout facts we need more passionate people who can renew our energy for subjects that we are already interested in or increase our interest and motivation into new subjects such as fighting climate change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Passionate People" /><category term="David Attenborough" /><category term="Brian Cox" /><summary type="html">I am interested in a wide range of subjects: the philosopher Wittgenstein, baking, poetry, mathematics, fishing. Quite a mix. But I claim no in-depth knowledge in any of these subjects. However, when I meet people who are passionate about a subject they inspire me to add it to my already long list!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/passionate-people.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Wikiart%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://www.wikiart.org/en/wassily-kandinsky/composition-viii-1923%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Tale Of Two Consultants</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/tale-of-two-consultants/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale Of Two Consultants" /><published>2020-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/tale-of-two-consultants</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/tale-of-two-consultants/">&lt;p&gt;I have reached an age where urinary infections are impacting on my quality of life. But my recent experiences with managing the problem has highlighted inconsistency in the urology expertise of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/&quot;&gt;NHS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been troubled for many years with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/urinary-tract-infections-utis/&quot;&gt;Urinary Track Infections ( UTI )&lt;/a&gt; because of an enlarged prostate. After a particularly bad infection which developed into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/prostatitis/&quot;&gt;Prostatitis&lt;/a&gt; I was put on a &lt;a href=&quot;http://dtinblack.github.io/medical-device-difference/&quot;&gt;bag catheter&lt;/a&gt; and then eventually moved onto &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/urinary-catheters/types/&quot;&gt;Intermittent Self Catheterisation ( ISC )&lt;/a&gt; to reduce the risk of any further UTIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My story starts with two consultants at different hospitals. Let me label them consultant A from the Urology Department in one hospital and consultant B from the other hospital. After recovering from Prostatitis an appointment was made with consultant A for further tests and to discuss the best way to manage my health problem. When I met with consultant A he advised me to stop using the catheters.  Life settled into making sure that I was drinking enough water and carefully marking out the location of public toilets! The situation was tolerable and I was beginning to feel that this was the new normal. When I left the consultant I made an appointment to review the situation in six months time however the hospital cancelled it closer to the date. When I hadn’t received a date for an appointment I contacted the hospital’s help line to be told that they hadn’t forgotten about me and I was still on the waiting list. After about 18 months and with no signs of an appointment with consultant A I discussed the situation with my GP and asked to see another consultant who had helped me in the past and I was switched to consultant B. I received an appointment within a week and if I hadn’t been travelling abroad I would have seen him before the month was out.  Two long haul flights later and I came down with a bad UTI which required 3 weeks on antibiotics by which time I was on my way see consultant B. In consultant B’s Urology department I we went through a series of tests and a questionnaire about how the medical problem was affecting the quality of my life. During the consultation I explained what had happened over the last few months and then consultant B explained that I had been sitting too long and should have used my catheters. He then went on to explain why I needed to use the catheters for the rest of my life and how they ensured that my bladder was emptying. When I was leaving I asked if he wanted to see me on a regular basis for example annually he replied that that would not be necessary because he felt that I was competent enough to manage the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the new catheter regime looking back I realise that I probably had a low level urinary infection since I saw consultant A. I now feel a lot better and the inconvenience of using the catheters is insignificant when compared to the improvement in my quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back over my experience with both consultants I realise that I had assumed that the level of expertise of urology consultants across the NHS would have been approximately the same. I say ‘approximately’ because I realise that due to the complexity of the human body and we all have different medical histories. However, I felt that my condition was not uncommon in older men and therefore the diagnosis and medical support should have been the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what could have contributed to the difference in advice? Lack of resources between the two hospitals could have contributed to the difference in advice with consultant A not having enough time to analyse the test results and have an in-depth discussion. There could be a wider issue of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.urologynews.uk.com/features/features/post/training-to-be-a-urologist-how-risky-is-it&quot;&gt;organisation of Urology&lt;/a&gt; departments which are under increasing pressure from changing employment contracts, a challenging on-call system,  changing training requirements as well as the increasing threat of litigation. All of these factors could have contributed to the difference in advice. However, I think that the difference comes down to the approach. Consultant A viewed my medical problem as a problem where he prescribed the appropriate solution a bit like a mechanic fixing a problem on a car. Consultant B looked at the problem from the patient perspective and by increasing my knowledge of the underlying problems and taking the time to explain why the course of action would improve the situation. Consultant B took a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.england.nhs.uk/ourwork/patient-participation/&quot;&gt;patient centric approach&lt;/a&gt; where I was seen as part of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember listening to a surgeon on the radio where he said that curing medical problems boils down to two approaches: medicine or surgery. We automatically think that medicine comes in a bottle or a tablet, but it could come in the shape of knowledge, and it is how it is applied that makes the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Big thanks to the Nurse who helped me overcome my fear of inserting a catheter as well showing me a few ‘tricks of the trade’, both urology consultants and their staff and my GPs for their on-going support.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="NHS" /><category term="UTI" /><category term="ISC" /><category term="Consultants Patient Centric" /><summary type="html">I have reached an age where urinary infections are impacting on my quality of life. But my recent experiences with managing the problem has highlighted inconsistency in the urology expertise of the NHS.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/tale-of-two-consultants.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22NHS%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://www.nhs.uk/service-search/other-services/Hospital/LocationSearch/8/Consultants%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Engineers in the Media</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/engineers-in-the-media/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Engineers in the Media" /><published>2019-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/engineers-in-the-media</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/engineers-in-the-media/">&lt;p&gt;Much of the public’s perception of engineering is gathered through the media, in particular the news on television, where somebody is wearing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hivis.net/&quot;&gt;HI-Vis vest&lt;/a&gt;, wearing a hard hat and discussing the failure of a large building project. It is no wonder that engineering struggles for recognition. How can this perception be changed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many years ago I was standing around a coffee machine with some colleagues discussing the usual office politics when one of them mentioned that they had to complete a project about the public perception of engineers through the media as part of their degree course. The puzzled silence was broken by a few more coins pushed into the coffee machine and as it filled up our cups a few examples emerged. First name was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin_Webster&quot;&gt;Kevin Webster&lt;/a&gt; who ran the garage in the long running TV soap opera &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.itv.com/coronationstreet&quot;&gt;Coronation Street&lt;/a&gt;. But was he an engineer or a mechanic? We weren’t sure.  Next was Tom Howard in the series &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0134250/plotsummary?ref_=tt_ov_pl&quot;&gt;Howards Way&lt;/a&gt; who designed yachts but always seemed to be in a psychological state close to a nervous breakdown. Anyway we only ever saw the back of a drawing board and there was a discussion about whether he was holding his pen correctly. Our time at the coffee machine was coming to an end and the last name that came up was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotty_(Star_Trek)&quot;&gt;Scotty&lt;/a&gt; from the long running series &lt;a href=&quot;https://intl.startrek.com/&quot;&gt;Star Trek&lt;/a&gt; who always managed to get a few more drops of power out of the overstretched warp drives just in time to save the USS Enterprise! We wished our colleague lots of luck with their project and headed back to our desks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years there have been some new TV series with engineering themes for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacGyver&quot;&gt;MacGyver&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/tvandradioblog/2014/oct/23/scorpion-tv-show-nerds-stereotypes&quot;&gt;Scorpion&lt;/a&gt; but their lead characters had super human skills which didn’t relate to everyday engineering. Other programmes included: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scrapheap_Challenge&quot;&gt;Scrapheap Challenge&lt;/a&gt; that shows the creativity of engineers but reminds me of the local blacksmith and not the high tech environment of a racing car company, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robotwars.tv/&quot;&gt;Robot Wars&lt;/a&gt; which is more about entertainment rather than making the world a better place, and a few documentaries for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00rmy1v&quot;&gt;Engineering for the World&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;Extreme Engineering&quot;&gt;Extreme Engineering&lt;/a&gt; but they concentrate on how the cars, planes etc. worked rather than the creativity and problem solving that the engineers used in developing them. There have been a few notable attempts to show the impact of engineering on peoples lives. For example the comedian Robbie Coltrane in his series &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0130393/&quot;&gt;Coltrane’s Planes and Automobiles&lt;/a&gt; tells the story of some of the greatest engines that have been built and explains how they work and their impact on society. Another is the film &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt7533152/&quot;&gt;The Boy Who Harnessed the Wind (2019)&lt;/a&gt; where a young schoolboy in Malawi overcomes many obstacles to save his village from drought by building a windmill to power an electric water pump. But overall there has been no improvement in media of engineers and therefore it should be no surprise that it is seen as a poor &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncchomelearning.co.uk/blog/these-are-the-highest-paying-jobs-in-the-uk/&quot;&gt;option&lt;/a&gt; compared to other careers such such as a marketing director, lawyer or celebrity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.engineeringuk.com/media/1576/7444_enguk18_synopsis_standalone_aw.pdf&quot;&gt;engineering skills&lt;/a&gt; crisis in the UK with around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.randstad.co.uk/career-advice/skills/uk-engineering-facing-skills-crisis-where-are-the-jobs/&quot;&gt;186,000 skilled recruits needed each year until 2024&lt;/a&gt;. The demand will only increase with major challenges such as the impact of climate change, feeding a growing population, and improvements in health and social care. Therefore we need to encourage more people into the profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What engineering needs is a ‘Brian Cox.’ to increase the awareness of engineering and inspire the next generation of engineers. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.physics.manchester.ac.uk/research/impact/the-brian-cox-effect/&quot;&gt;Brian Cox Effect&lt;/a&gt; has increased the number of people taking A-Level physics by 20% and UCAS reported that applications to university physics courses increase by 52%. We need to see a similar improvement in the take up of engineering. The engineering equivalent of Brian Cox would bring their enthusiasm and communication skills to a wealth of material. For example how about a series on the engineers behind the everyday things that we use and affect our lives such as heating, electricity, transportation, the internet or mobile phones?  Or covering the engineering being used in current research for example using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/12/191209131952.htm&quot;&gt;Formula 1 technology being applied in the construction of skyscrapers&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/12/191216122415.htm&quot;&gt;using AI to optimise the materials used in constructing solar panels&lt;/a&gt;. Finally speculating about future engineering challenges, for example the engineering that will be required to scale up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/lab-grown-meat/&quot;&gt;lab grown meat&lt;/a&gt; to full production so that we can reduce the amount of the Green House Gas methane from cattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I doubt whether there will be any coffee machines in the future for people to gather around and discuss the issues of the day. But wherever they gather lets hope that the discussion starts about an engineering programme that they have seen on television, or other devices, that is presented with the same clarity and enthusiasm as Brian Cox!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Engineers" /><category term="Media" /><category term="TV" /><summary type="html">Much of the public’s perception of engineering is gathered through the media, in particular the news on television, where somebody is wearing a HI-Vis vest, wearing a hard hat and discussing the failure of a large building project. It is no wonder that engineering struggles for recognition. How can this perception be changed?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/engineers-in-the-media.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Revolvy%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://www.revolvy.com/page/WORST-Engineering-Mistakes-In-History!?stype=videos&amp;cmd=list&amp;sml=wi0QdCpEo_0%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Leaders Wanted To Tackle Climate Change</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/engineering-savvy-leaders/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Leaders Wanted To Tackle Climate Change" /><published>2019-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/engineering-savvy%20leaders</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/engineering-savvy-leaders/">&lt;p&gt;Many years ago in an engineering lecture, one of my fellow students put his hand up and asked the lecturer a cheeky “What is the point of this degree?” The answer has stayed with me ever since and with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_crisis&quot;&gt;climate change&lt;/a&gt; starting to grip &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_crisis&quot;&gt;political discussion&lt;/a&gt; his reply has become more relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lecture was part of a degree in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_College_of_Agricultural_Engineering&quot;&gt;Agriculture Engineering&lt;/a&gt; which covered a broad range of skills from mechanical to electronic engineering and included science and economics. We were developing skills that would be used to improve the productivity of agriculture and horticulture through mechanisation and automation.  It was the early &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/personalfinance/comment/9387510/1970s-Britain-Families-were-forced-to-tighten-their-belts-and-contend-with-high-inflation.html&quot;&gt;seventies&lt;/a&gt; and there was a lot of economic and political turmoil and therefore there was an air of foreboding. The lecturer, who was a favourite amongst the students, took the question in his stride and replied “if society ever broke down then as an Agriculture engineer you would survive because we could grow crops, rear animals and build machines to generate electricity and pump water”.  However, in the silence that followed his reply, we looked at each other, rolled our eyes, and quickly got back to his lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lecturer’s reply remained with me more as a curiosity rather than a serious comment. But recently there has been a number of reports published where his reply may be relevant. For example the paper: &lt;a href=&quot;http://insight.cumbria.ac.uk/id/eprint/4166/&quot;&gt;Deep Adaption: A Map for Navigating Climate Tragedy&lt;/a&gt; concluded that all of the initiatives discussed to reduce the human activity on climate change will fail and there will be “a near-term collapse in society”. In a similar vein &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/simon-kuper&quot;&gt;Simon Kuper’s&lt;/a&gt; article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/d7ec60e6-9b9a-11e9-b8ce-8b459ed04726&quot;&gt;Emission impossible? Harsh facts on climate change&lt;/a&gt; where he supports the view that climate change will happen and it will take global collective action to limit climate change. He goes on to say that
the current political leaders are using green ideology as add-ons to policies that are contributing to the climate change and will not be effective. The article continues “As temperatures rise, the hotter days will start to dominate politics with problems such as less water, more illness, lower productivity and unliveable regions of Europe, a permanent cordon.” And points out that political debate will eventually revolve around which huge engineering projects to finance, and that the current political leaders do not have the expertise to make those decisions.  The article concludes with the identification of a new type of climate leader who has an engineering background. Currently, there appears to be a lack of leaders with an engineering background, for example amongst the &lt;a href=&quot;https://researchbriefings.parliament.uk/ResearchBriefing/Summary/CBP-7483#fullreport&quot;&gt;UK MPs&lt;/a&gt; there are none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the type of engineering background required will be significantly different than the one that I was trained in over forty years ago. Scientific knowledge about the environment and the climate along with huge advances in technology provides new opportunities to tackle the problems of climate change.  And although there are new branches of engineering for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2011/feb/18/geo-engineering&quot;&gt;geoengineering&lt;/a&gt; specialising in reducing the effect of CO2 or limiting the sunlight that reaches the earth they do not face up to the possibility that the initiatives will fail and therefore there will be social breakdown. What is required is a new type of engineer that uses a broad range of engineering skills but also takes the social context into account when mitigating the impact of climate change. The engineering-savvy leader will have many &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.supplychain247.com/article/six_leadership_traits_of_sir_winston_churchill&quot;&gt;traits&lt;/a&gt; For example, being skilled in the use of both the media and social media, and using it to effectively communicate to different sections of society at the local and national level. Image persuading a small seaside town that they will all have to move inland because of rising sea levels or convincing different governments to build a transnational water pipeline so that drinking water can be transported from a wet country to a dry one.  Also, because of the global nature of climate change they will have to be recognised as strong climate change leaders with enough credibility to make the compromises that will be required between nations. They will need to be critical about the current and future initiatives to mitigate the effects of climate change so that resources will not be wasted on unfeasible ideas as well as cutting through a cacophony of consultants predictions to get to the core of the problems. They will be passionate, with clear goals and show great courage in taking action against a background of criticism and setbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although our lecturer’s reply to the question was about how we would survive as individuals if society broke down, the future leaders will be looking at societies and nations as a whole and if the increase in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/natural-disasters&quot;&gt;extreme weather&lt;/a&gt; is a sign of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_crisis&quot;&gt;climate crisis&lt;/a&gt; then lets hope that new type of leader emerges soon!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Climate Change" /><category term="Agricultural Engineering" /><category term="Leadership" /><category term="Climate Crisis" /><summary type="html">Many years ago in an engineering lecture, one of my fellow students put his hand up and asked the lecturer a cheeky “What is the point of this degree?” The answer has stayed with me ever since and with climate change starting to grip political discussion his reply has become more relevant.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/engineering-savvy-leaders.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22The%20University%20of%20Adelaide%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://www.adelaide.edu.au/industry-government/news/list/2019/08/02/how-do-we-meet-our-climate-change-targets%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Health Advice From Uncle Albert</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/anecdotal-evidence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Health Advice From Uncle Albert" /><published>2019-10-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/anecdotal-evidence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/anecdotal-evidence/">&lt;p&gt;During my regular chats with my mum, the conversation quickly turns to her health problems and how her GP has not helped. Yet the health advice from her Chiropodist is fiercely defended when I challenge its scientific basis.  Why does the health advice from her Chiropodist, which is anecdotal, have such a strong influence on my mum ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remembered listening to a radio programme where the concept of an Uncle Albert Syndrome was discussed. There is a lot of public health information available for example on reducing weight, a balanced diet, increasing exercise,  reducing alcohol consumption and how stoping smoking will extend your life. But in every family there is an ‘Uncle Albert’ who drinks like a fish, smokes like a chimney and has a balanced diet of cooked breakfast, fish and chips and pies and who is living a healthy life well into their eighties! When compared to public health information, which is science based, many people follow Uncle Albert!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons for people relying on their Uncle Albert for health guidance rather than science based health information. For example the reliability of public health information. There seems to be regular headlines that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/health-and-families/features/medical-contradictions-so-bad-its-good-for-you-2361404.html&quot;&gt;contradict&lt;/a&gt; some earlier study. Should we eat more or less butter, drink a glass of red wine per day or abstain, drink more or less coffee? - all of these questions, and many more have swung between yes - maybe - no over the last thirty to forty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are subtle reasons for accepting health evidence from Uncle Albert. In the case of my mum’s Chiropodist, who has many clients, he can gather examples of what medical solutions are working and what is not. With the NHS resources stretched he is filling the gap between them and low level aches and pains that irritate but are not serious enough to book an appointment with the GP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of my chats with my mum, I usually receive clear instructions to go off and buy whatever her Chiropodist has recommended which luckily only requires a few clicks on a web site. His track record so far is: the special fruit juice for her stomach which didn’t work and had adverse consequences, the copper band for arthritis is still under review and the knee brace to reduce the pain on her knee seems to be working. The easy acceptance of evidence for health of an Uncle Albert is very complex. For many of the complex and serious health problems such as cancer, diabetes etc.  then a science based approach will be always be needed. But for the everyday minor aches and pains then it looks as though finding a good Chiropodist could be the best solution.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Anecdotal Evidence" /><category term="Scientfic Evidence" /><summary type="html">During my regular chats with my mum, the conversation quickly turns to her health problems and how her GP has not helped. Yet the health advice from her Chiropodist is fiercely defended when I challenge its scientific basis. Why does the health advice from her Chiropodist, which is anecdotal, have such a strong influence on my mum ?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22background%22=%3E%22backgrounds/general-background.jpg%22,%20%22feature%22=%3E%22features/anecdotal-evidence.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3E%22Asian%20Scientist%22,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22https://www.asianscientist.com/2016/07/features/grand-challenges-for-science-21st-century-ntu-singapore/%22%7D" /></entry></feed>